Guide to the Piet Mondrian Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Piet Mondrian papers
1881-1945
GEN MSS 1102
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
2.54
(8 boxes)
The collection consists of the writings and personal papers of Piet Mondrian, in addition to writings about him and the DeStijl movement. Most of Mondrian's writings were arranged and annotated by Harry Holtzman and Martin S. James for their volume The New Art, the New Life: the Complete Writings of Piet Mondrian (Boston: G. K. Hall, 1986). Some of the writings also were annotated by Mondrian's colleagues Michel Seuphor and Georges Vantongerloo. Personal papers include items such as Mondrian's birth certifications and passports, leases for his studios in Paris and New York, his United States war ration books, his will, and an undated drawing by Mondrian. Also present are a few autograph and typed letters, signed, from friends and colleagues in the arts.
Mondrian, Piet, 1872-1944
Steiner, Rudolf, 1861-1925
Doesburg, Theo van, 1883-1931
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Harry Holtzman, 1983-1985.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Existence and Location of Copies
Portions of the collection were microfilmed and appear on Beinecke Library Vault Films 889 and 2598.
Associated Materials
Harry Holtzman Papers (GEN MSS 819).
Piet Mondrian (1872-1944)
Dutch artist, immigrated to the United States in 1940 and died in New York in 1944.
Scope and Contents
The collection consists of the writings and personal papers of Piet Mondrian, in addition to writings about him and the De Stijl movement. Most of Mondrian's writings were arranged and annotated by Harry Holtzman and Martin S. James for their volume The New Art, the New Life: the Complete Writings of Piet Mondrian (Boston: G. K. Hall, 1986). Some of the writings also were annotated by Mondrian's colleagues Michel Seuphor and Georges Vantongerloo. Personal papers include items such as Mondrian's birth certifications and passport, leases for his studios in Paris and New York, his United States war ration books, and his will. Also present are a few autograph and typed letters, signed, from friends and colleagues in the arts, and an undated drawing by Mondrian. Along with the papers are publications by others that were owned by Mondrian, some with his autograph annotations, and issues of the journal De Stijl.
Arrangement
Organized into two series: I. Writings, 1917-1945. II. Personal Papers, 1881-1944.
Artists -- Netherlands; Artists -- Netherlands -- Archives; Authors, Dutch; Authors, Dutch -- Archives; De Stijl (Art movement); Neoplasticism; Drawings (visual works) -- Netherlands -- 20th Century; Legal documents -- United States -- 20th Century; Artists -- Netherlands -- 20th Century; Authors, Dutch -- 20th Century; Austin, Arthur Everett, 1900-1957; Davis, Stuart, 1892-1964; Duchamp, Marcel, 1887-1968; Eesteren, Cornelis van, 1897-1988; Holtzman, Harry, 1912-1987; James, Martin S.; Mondrian, Piet, 1872-1944; Seuphor, Michel, 1901-1999; Steiner, Rudolf, 1861-1925 ( Verslag van de voordrachten); Doesburg, Theo van, 1883-1931; Vantongerloo, Georges, 1886-1965; Zethraeus, Agatha, 1872-1966; Cercle et carré (Group); Museum Folkwang Essen; Société théosophique de France
- Writings, 1917-1945; Series I; 1.25; (3 boxes)
  Arrangement
  Series I is organized into three subseries: Essays, Partial Essays, and Notes.
  Scope and Contents
  The subseries Essays and Partial Essays hold writings by Mondrian in autograph manuscript, typescript, and printed versions. Material in the Notes subseries are sheets and scraps of paper, including the backs of envelopes and letters he had received in the mail, on which Mondrian jotted his thoughts and theories. The notes were grouped in themes or subjects and arranged by Harry Holtzman; they remain in that order, accompanied by his typed transcripts or photocopies of the transcripts, which were corrected and annotated.
  - Essays
    Arranged roughly chronologically.
    - "De Nieuwe Beelding in de schilderkunst" [The New Plastic in Painting], 1917-1918 (Box 1, Folder 1-2)
      A set of detached pages from De Stijl: vol. 1, no. 1, p. 2-6, no. 2, p. 13-18, no. 3, p. 29-31, no. 4, p. 41-45, no. 5, p. 49-54, no. 7, p. 73-77, no. 8, p. 88-91, no. 9, p. 102-108, no. 10, p. 121-124, no. 11, p. 125-134, no. 12, p. 140-147, and vol. 2, no. 2:, p. 14-19), accompanied by undated photocopies.
      Holtzman 1
    - "Dialog von der neuen Gestaltung" [Dialogue on the New Plastic], 1919, undated (Box 1, Folder 3-4)
      Manuscript in German, in an unknown hand, signed and dated by Mondrian, February 1919 (22 p.).
      Second manuscript, also in German, in an unknown hand (10 p.).
      Accompanied by undated photocopies.
      Holtzman 2
    - "Natuurlijke en abstracte realiteit" [Natural and Abstract Reality, 1919-1920], undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
      Photocopies of De Stijl vol. 2, no. 8, p. 85-89, no 9, p. 97-99, no. 10, p. 109-113, no. 11, p. 121-125, no. 12, p. 133-137; and vol. 3, no. 3, p. 15-19, no. 4, p. 27-31, no. 5, p. 41-44, no. 6, p. 54-56, no. 7, p. 58-60, no. 8, p. 65-69, no. 9, p. 73-76, no. 10, p. 81-84; annotated by Harry Holtzman and Martin James.
      Holtzman 3
    - "De Groote boulevards" [The Grand Boulevards], 1920 Mar 27 (Box 1, Folder 6)
      Newspaper clippings from De Nieuwe Amsterdammer, vol. 273.
      Holtzman 4
    - "Klein restaurant - Palmszondag" [Small Restaurant - Palm Sunday], 1920 Apr 12 (Box 1, Folder 7)
      Autograph manuscript, signed (8 p.); annotated by Martin James.
      Holtzman 5
    - Le Néo-Plasticisme [Neo-Plasticism: General Principle of Plastic Equivalence] (Paris: Editions de l'Effort Moderne Léonce Rosenberg, 1920) (Box 1, Folder 8)
      Five copies and one extra front cover; copy 1 with autograph correction on page 6; copy 3 with autograph correction on page 14.
      Holtzman 6
    - "De 'Bruiteurs futuristes Italiens' en 'het' nieuwe in de muziek" [The "Italian Futurist Bruiteurs" and the "New" in Music], 1921 (Box 1, Folder 9)
      Detached leaves from De Stijl, vol. 4, no. 8 (August 1921), p. 113-120, and vol. 4, no. 9 (September 1921), p. 129-136; plates lacking.
      Holtzman 7
    - "Het Néo-plasticisme (de Nieuwe Beelding) en zijn (hare) realiseering in de muziek" [Neo-Plasticism and its Realization in Music], 1922 (Box 1, Folder 10)
      Detached leaves from De Stijl, vol. 5, no. 1 (January 1922), p. 1-8, and no. 2 (February 1922), p. 1-8, with autograph annotations by Mondrian; plates lacking.
      Holtzman 8A
    - "La manifestation du néo-plasticisme dans la musique et les bruiteurs futuristes italiens", 1922 (Box 1, Folder 11)
      Detached leaves from La vie des lettres et des arts (Paris: 1922), p. 131-144; some annotations by Mondrian; numbers by Martin James.
      Holtzman 8B
    - "De realiseering van het Neo-plasticisme in verre toekomst en in de huidge architectuur" [The Realization of Neo-plasticism in the Distant Future and in Architecture Today], 1922 (Box 1, Folder 12)
      Detached leaves from De Stijl vol. 5, no. 4 (April 1922), p. 41-48, and vol. 5, no. 5 (May 1922), p. 65-72; autograph corrections by Mondrian.
      Holtzman 9
    - "Moet de schilderkunst minderwaardig zijn aan de bouwkunst?" [Is Painting Inferior to Architecture?], 1923 (Box 1, Folder 13)
      Detached leaves from De Stijl, vol. 6, no. 5 (1923), p. 61-64.
      Holtzman 10
    - "Het Neo-plasticisme", 1923 (Box 1, Folder 14)
      Manuscript in an unknown hand, with autograph corrections by Mondrian and pencil notes by Martin James (5 p.). On recto of p. 5: manuscript draft of a letter signed by Mondrian.
      Autograph manuscript of a portion of the work (1 p.)
      "Het Neo-plasticisme" in Merz, vol. 6 (October 1923), p. 53-54; with autograph annotations by Mondrian.
      Accompanied by a typed letter, signed, from Robert L. Herbert to Harry Holtzman (July 3, 1978) with a photocopy of an autograph essay by Mondrian (now in Katherine S. Dreier Papers (YCAL MSS 101), Box 24, folder 710).
      Holtzman 11A
    - "Die neue Gestaltung in der Musik und die futuristischen italienischen Bruitisten" [The Manifestation of Néo-plasticism in Music and the Italian Futurist Brutteurs], 1923 (Box 1, Folder 15)
      Detached leaves from De Stijl, vol. 6, no. 1 (March 1923), p. 1-9 and vol. 6, no. 2 (April 1923), p. 19-25), annotated in an unidentified hand.
      Holtzman 11B
    - "Geen Axioma maar beeldend principe" [No Axiom but Plastic Principle], circa 1924 (Box 1, Folder 16)
      Manuscript in an unknown hand of English translation of (3p.), with photocopy of typescript with autograph annotations by Martin James.
      Photocopy from DeStijl, vol. 6, no. 6-7 (1924), p. 83-84.
      Holtzman 12
    - "De huif naar den wind" [Blown by the Wind], undated (Box 1, Folder 17)
      Photocopy from De Stijl, vol. 6, no. 6-7 (1924), p. 88-88.
      Holtzman 13
    - "A bas l'harmonie traditionelle" [Down with Traditional Harmony], 1924 (Box 1, Folder 18)
      Typescript, Paris, 1924 (4 p.) with corrections by Enrico Prampolini, accompanied by a typed letter to Enrico Prampolini (January 22, 1924) and a typed letter, signed, from Prampolini to Harry Holtzman (July 11, 1960).
      Holtzman 14
    - "Les arts et la beauté de notre ambiance tangible" [The Arts and the Beauty of Our Tangible Surroundings], 1924 (Box 1, Folder 19)
      Detached leaves from Manomètre, vol. 6 (August 1924), p. 107-108; with Martin James' notes.
      Holtzman 15
    - "L'Evolution de l'humanité est l'évolution de l'art" [The Evolution of Humanity is the Evolution of Art], 1924 (Box 1, Folder 20)
      In Bulletin de "l'Effort Moderne", no. 9 (November 1924); autograph annotations by Martin James.
      Holtzman 16
    - "L'Architecture future néo-plasticienne" [The Neo-plastic Architecture of the Future, 1925], undated (Box 1, Folder 21)
      Typescripts of Mondrian's essay and "L'Evolution de l'Architecture moderne en Hollande" by Theo van Doesburg (7 p.).
      Holtzman 17
    - Neue Gestaltung / Neoplastizismus / Nieuwe Beelding (München: Albert Langen Verlag, 1925) (Box 1, Folder 22)
      Bauhaus Bücher 5
      Holtzman 52
    - "L'Art purement Abstrait" [Purely Abstract Art], 1926
      Detached leaves from Vouloir (March 1926); autograph annotations by Mondrian.
      Holtzman 18
    - "L'Expression plastique nouvelle dans la peinture" [New Plastic Expression in Painting], 1926
      Detached leaves from Cahiers d'Art, vol. 1, no. 7 (1926), p. 181-183; with autograph annotations by Martin James.
      Holtzman 19
    - "Neo-plasticisme. De Woning - De Straat - De Stad" [Neo-plasticism: Home--Street--City], 1927 (Box 1, Folder 23)
      Detached leaves from International Revue, vol. 1, no. 10 (1927), p. 12-18; with autograph annotations by Martin James.
      Holtzman 20
    - "De jazz en de Neo-plastiek" [Jazz and Neo-plasticism], 1927 (Box 1, Folder 24)
      Detached leaves from International Revue, vol. 1, no. 12 (1927), p. 421-427; with autograph annotations by Mondrian.
      Holtzman 22
    - "Ne pas se occupe de la forme et de la coleur...", 1929 (Box 1, Folder 25)
      Autograph manuscript, signed, in French, dated December 1929 (1 p.). Printed in Cercle et Carré, 1929.
      Accompanied by a typescript of an English translation by Harry Holtzman.
      Holtzman 23
    - "Die rein abstrakte Kunst" (l'art abstrait pur) [Pure Abstract Art], 1929 Oct 26
      Clipping from Neue Zürcher Zeitung, no. 2060 (October 26, 1929).
      Holtzman 24
    - [A note on fashion], circa 1930 (Box 1, Folder 26)
      Detached leaf from unidentified French periodical.
      Holtzman 25
    - "L'Art réaliste et l'art superréaliste (La Morphoplastique et la Néoplastique)" [Realist and Superrealist Art (Morphoplastic and Neo-Plastic)], 1930 (Box 1, Folder 27)
      Photocopy of autograph manuscript, signed; Paris, January 1930 (10p.)
      Typescript, signed, with autograph corrections, Paris, March 1930 (24 p.) and carbon typescript, signed, with autograph corrections and annotations by Martin James; some pages missing in the carbon copy.
      Detached leaves from Cercle et Carré, no. 2 (April 15, 1930), p. 1-4.
      Holtzman 26
    - "Le Cubisme et la Néoplastique", 1930 (Box 1, Folder 28)
      Typescript, signed, with autograph corrections, Paris, March 25, 1930 (12 p.).
      Carbon typescript, signed, with autograph corrections, Paris, March 25, 1930 (12 p.).
      Carbon typescript, signed, with autograph corrections by Mondrian and autograph annotations by Michel Seuphor, Paris, March 25, 1930 (12 p.).
      Holtzman 27
    - "De l'art abstrait: reponse de Piet Mondrian", 1931
      Detached leaves from Cahiers d'Art, vol. 6 (1931).
      Holtzman 28
    - "Un museé contemporain international" (An International Contemporary Museum), 1931 (Box 1, Folder 29)
      Autograph manuscript, signed, August 1931 (5 p.).
      Autograph manuscript, signed, with pencil notes on verso (2 p.).
      Holtzman 29
    - "L'Art nouveau - la vie nouvelle (La culture des rapports purs)" [The New Art - the New Life: the Culture of Pure Relationships], 1931 (Box 2, Folder 30)
      Typescript with autograph corrections, Paris, December 1931 (79 p.); one page of autograph manuscript inserted between pages 57-58. Marked "Final Copy."
      Holtzman 30Aa
    - "L'Art nouveau - la vie nouvelle (La culture des rapports purs)", 1931 (Box 2, Folder 31)
      Typescript carbon with autograph annotations and corrections, Paris December 1931 (79 p.).
      Holtzman 30B
    - "L'Art nouveau - la vie nouvelle (La culture des rapports purs)", 1931 (Box 2, Folder 32)
      Typescript carbon with autograph corrections by Mondrian, and autograph annotations by Michel Seuphor and Georges Vantongerloo; title changed by Mondrian to "L'Art révélaeur," Paris December 1931 (79 p.).
    - "L'Art nouveau - la vie nouvelle (La culture des rapports purs)", 1931 (Box 2, Folder 33)
      Typescript carbon with manuscript annotations, some by Mondrian, Paris, December 1931 (79 p.); bound with stencil-titled cover lightly inscribed in pencil "Master copy 2."
      Holtzman 30C
    - Introduction to "L'Art nouveau - la vie nouvelle (la culture des rapports purs)", 1932 (Box 2, Folder 34)
      Autograph manuscript, Paris, June 1932 (12 p.).
      Holtzman 31
    - "The True Value of Oppositions in Life and Art" [La Vraie valeur des oppositions], 1934 (Box 2, Folder 35)
      Autograph manuscript, signed (6 p.) and typescript with autograph corrections (4 p.), Paris, December 1934.
      With French translation: typescript (6 p.) and carbon with autograph corrections, December 1934.
      Holtzman 32
    - "Réponse à une enquête" [Response to an inquiry], 1935
      Detached leaves from Cahiers d'Art, vol. 10, no. 1-4 (1935); accompanied by photocopy of a portion of the magazine.
      Holtzman 33
    - "Three Notes", 1937 (Box 2, Folder 36)
      Autograph manuscript, in French (2 p.); accompanied by photocopy and photocopy of article printed in Transition, vol. 26 (1937).
      Holtzman 35
    - "Kunst zonder onderwerp" "Kunst ohne objekte" [Art Without Subject], 1938 (Box 2, Folder 37)
      Autograph manuscript, signed, March 1938 (6 p.), accompanied by photocopies of printed versions in Dutch and German.
      Holtzman 34
    - "Photos I et II: neo-plastique" [Photos I and II: Neo-Plastic], 1938 (Box 2, Folder 38)
      Two autograph manuscript drafts (2 p.), one signed, March 1938.
      Holtzman 36
    - [Neo-Plastic], 1938 (Box 2, Folder 39)
      Detached page from Werk (August 1938), p. 251.
    - "A New Religion?", circa 1939 (Box 2, Folder 40)
      Autograph manuscript essay in notebook, accompanied by photocopy of typed transcription.
      Holtzman 39
    - "Art Shows the Evil of Nazi and Soviet Oppressive Tendencies", circa 1940 (Box 2, Folder 41)
      Autograph manuscript, corrected (27 p.).
      Holtzman 40a
    - "On Oppression of Art by the Dictators", circa 1940 (Box 2, Folder 42)
      Typescript, corrected (9 p.).
      Holtzman 40c
    - "Liberation from Oppression in Art and Life", 1940 (Box 2, Folder 43)
      Typescript with autograph corrections (20 p.).
      Holtzman 41Aa
    - "Oppression in Art and Life", 1940 Dec (Box 2, Folder 44)
      Typescript, signed, with autograph corrections; also annotated by Harry Holtzman, December 1940 (19 p.).
      Holtzman 41Ab
      Holtzman 40b (pages 7-8)
    - "Plastic Art Shows the Evil of Oppression", 1940 (Box 2, Folder 45)
      Autograph manuscript (11 p.).
      Holtzman 41Ba
    - "The Liberation from Oppression in Art and Life", 1940-1942 (Box 2, Folder 46)
      Autograph manuscript and typescript, signed, annotated, and corrected, dated February 1940, February 1941, and January 1942 (25 p.).
      Holtzman 41Bb
    - "Oppression in Art and Life", 1940 (Box 2, Folder 47)
      Autograph manuscript, page 22 signed and dated May 1940 (33 p.).
      Holtzman 41Bc
    - "Art and Life Towards the Liberation from Oppression", 1940 (Box 2, Folder 48)
      Autograph manuscript and typescript with additions and corrections (23 p.).
      Holtzman 41Bd
    - "Abstract Art", circa 1941 (Box 2, Folder 49)
      Autograph manuscript (4 p.).
      Holtzman 42
    - "Abstract Art", 1941 Oct (Box 2, Folder 50)
      Autograph manuscript, signed (5 p.), and typescript with autograph corrections (3 p.), October 1941; accompanied by carbon typescript transcription.
      Holtzman 43
    - "Abstract Art", 1941 Nov (Box 2, Folder 51)
      Autograph manuscript, signed (4 p.).
      Holtzman 44
    - "Toward the true vision of reality", 1941 (Box 2, Folder 52-53)
      Autograph manuscript (21 p.) and autograph notes (10 p.), with printed version: Toward the True Vision of Reality (New York: Valentine Gallery, 1941) (8 copies).
      Holtzman 45
    - "Abstract Art", 1941 (Box 2, Folder 54)
      Autograph manuscript (6 p.).
      Holtzman 46
    - "Reality and Plastic Art" and "Plastic Art: Reflex of Reality", 1942 (Box 2, Folder 55)
      Autograph manuscript (10 p.) and autograph manuscript (9 p.), accompanied by edited typed transcript.
      Holtzman 48
    - Plastic Art and Pure Plastic Art, 1937, and other essays, 1941-1943 (New York: Wittenborn, 1945) (Box 2, Folder 56)
      Holtzman 51
  - Partial Essays
    Subject-based titles supplied by Harry Holtzman.
    - [Space determination], circa 1942 (Box 2, Folder 57)
      Autograph manuscript (12 p.), accompanied by edited photocopy of typed transcription.
      Holtzman 49
    - [The meaning of beauty], circa 1942-1943 (Box 2, Folder 58)
      Autograph manuscript (6 p.), accompanied by edited photocopy of typed transcription.
      Holtzman 56
    - [Self-destruction as construction], circa 1942 (Box 2, Folder 59)
      Autograph manuscript (3 p.), accompanied by edited photocopy of typed transcription.
      Holtzman 57
    - [Liberation from oppression in plastic art and in life], circa 1940 (Box 2, Folder 60)
      Autograph manuscript (2 p.), accompanied by edited photocopy of typed transcription.
      Holtzman 58
    - [Two incomplete notations on the word "plastic"], undated (Box 2, Folder 61)
      Autograph manuscript (2 p.), accompanied by carbon typescript transcription.
      Holtzman 59
    - [Meaning of plastic expression], circa 1942-1943 (Box 2, Folder 62)
      Autograph manuscript (3 p.), accompanied by edited carbon typescript transcription.
      Holtzman 60
    - [Plastic expression: painting, sculpture, architecture], circa 1942-1943 (Box 2, Folder 63)
      Holtzman 61
    - [Volumes and planes], circa 1942 (Box 2, Folder 64)
      Holtzman 62
  - Notes
    Groupings and subject-based titles created by Harry Holtzman. The material was once kept in a three-ring binder titled by him "P.M./NOTES/1938-43/137/INDIVIDUAL/PIECES."
    - 2. True vision: notes for interview, undated (Box 3, Folder 65)
    - 3-4. Religion, undated (Box 3, Folder 66-67)
    - 5. Logic - Time - Evolution, life - Art, undated (Box 3, Folder 68)
    - 6. Art - Reflex of Reality - Fantasy transformation, undated (Box 3, Folder 69)
      Includes notes written on the verso of a typed letter, signed, from Peggy Guggenheim (September 11, 1942).
    - 7. Art - Modern art - Tradition, undated (Box 3, Folder 70)
    - 8a-8b. Tragic, undated (Box 3, Folder 71-72)
    - 9. [Unidentified], undated (Box 3, Folder 73)
    - 10. Destruction, undated (Box 3, Folder 74)
    - 11. Instinct - Intuition - Culture - Education, undated (Box 3, Folder 75)
    - 12. Structure - Dynamic movement, undated (Box 3, Folder 76)
    - 12a. Space expression, undated (Box 3, Folder 77)
    - 13. Architecture, undated (Box 3, Folder 78)
    - 14. Metropolis, undated (Box 3, Folder 79)
    - 15. Teaching, undated (Box 3, Folder 80)
    - 16. Fragments, undated (Box 3, Folder 81)
- Other Papers, 1881-1944; Series II; 1.04; (3 boxes)
  Series II is organized into two subseries: Personal Papers and Publications.
  The series contains personal documents, correspondence, and small publications that Mondrian brought with him to the United States, or acquired here after his arrival, as well as a single drawing undated by him. Publications contains books owned by Mondrian as well as writings about Mondrian by others. Unless otherwise noted, items in this series appeared in the Holtzman inventory under the numbers 51, 52, and 55.
  - Personal Papers
    Arranged chronologically.
    - Date of birth certifications, 1881-1912 (Box 4, Folder 82)
    - Diploma to teach drawing, 1889 Dec 11 (Box 4, Folder 83)
    - Diploma for Secondary School Art Teaching, 1892 Sep 10
    - Certificate of Good Character, 1892 Oct 24 (Box 4, Folder 84)
    - Membership Certificate, Theosophical Society, 1909 (Box 4, Folder 85)
    - Extrait du Registre d'Immatriculation, 1912 May 11 (Box 4, Folder 86)
    - Lease for studio at 26 rue du Depart, Paris, 1922 (Box 4, Folder 87)
    - Business cards, 26 rue du Depart, Paris, circa 1922 (Box 4, Folder 88)
    - Subscription form for Bulletin de "l'Effort Moderne", 1924 (Box 4, Folder 89)
    - Newspaper clippings about Mondrian, 1926-1942 (Box 4, Folder 90)
    - Dutch passport, 1928 (Box 4, Folder 91)
    - Autograph letter, signed, from Ernst Gosebruch, Museum Folkwang Essen, 1928 Sep 18 (Box 4, Folder 92)
    - Autograph letter, signed, from Cornelis van Eesteren, also signed by fourteen architects and designers, 1932 Feb 29 (Box 4, Folder 93)
      Regarding their intention to purchase a Mondrian painting to present to one of the museums in Amsterdam in honor of Mondrian's 60th birthday.
    - Carte d'Identite, 1934 (Box 4, Folder 94)
    - Typed letter, signed, from forty-three architects attending Congrès Internationaux d'Architecture Moderne (CIAM), 1935 Jun 11 (Box 4, Folder 95)
    - Typed letter, signed, from A. Everett Austin Jr., Wadsworth Atheneum, Hartford, Connecticut, 1936 Apr 6 (Box 4, Folder 96)
    - Autograph letter, signed, to Harry Holtzman requesting invitation to immigrate to United States, 1938 Sep 7 (Box 4, Folder 97)
    - Typed letter, signed, from Société Théosophique de France with membership card, 1939 Feb 3 (Box 4, Folder 98)
    - Article on romance clipped from a London newspaper, 1939 Mar 4 (Box 4, Folder 99)
    - National Registration Card, United Kingdom, 1940 May 22 (Box 4, Folder 100)
    - Alien Registration Receipt Card, United States, 1940 (Box 4, Folder 101)
    - Identification card, Quota Immigration Visa, United States Department of State and Department of Labor, 1940 Aug 19 (Box 4, Folder 102)
    - Leases (3) for apartment at 353 East 56th Street, New York, 1940-1942 (Box 4, Folder 103)
    - Social Security Card, United States, circa 1941 (Box 4, Folder 104)
    - Autograph note, signed, from Marcel Duchamp (left by Duchamp on Mondrian's door), 1941 June (Box 4, Folder 105)